Bill Martin

bill@billmartin.io | (813) 310-6417 | Manchester, NH



Summary

Full stack senior software engineer with 10 years of experience designing, building, and deploying high volume, load-balanced LAMP/JavaScript web applications and APIs in a fast-paced environment. Passionate about clean code, DevOps processes, scalability, learning new technologies, and making an impact.

Professional Experience

HealthPlan Services, Tampa, FL

April 2010 – Current

Lead Developer | 2018 - Current

- Directly lead, mentor, and handle project sprint planning for a team of 8 web developers
- Oversee 18 PHP7 web applications and 25 cronjobs and services spanning PCI-compliant payment processing, billing, commissions, quoting, enrollment, policy management, and customer service management business domains as subject matter expert
- Handle production deployments, and coordinate with project managers, business analysts, QA, product owners, and stakeholders from project inception to completion

Senior Web Developer | 2016 - 2018

- Standardized code review process, enforce code standards, and develop documentation and a knowledgebase to guide 13 developers across 2 teams.
- Mentored 10 junior developers to develop a new framework and group insurance platform consisting of agent, employer, member, and policy management PHP7 web applications
- Led a team of 4 web developers to convert dozens of web applications, cronjobs, and web services from PHP4/PHP5 to PHP7, which required coordination of servers, load balancing, and developing a scalable, in-house tool to update the entire codebase.

Web Developer | 2010 - 2016

- Designed and developed PHP5 XML/JSON web APIs & batch jobs that tokenized payments for enrollments from the HPS health insurance marketplace that brought in \$3 million/year insuring members under United Healthcare, Aetna, Cigna, and more
- Setup Idaho, California, and Kentucky state marketplaces to accept payments through a payment processing web application used on Healthcare.gov which processes 1 million payments per year, making up 21% of the Federal and State Marketplace volume
- Built PHP 5 quoting web application that calculated new premiums for changes against existing policies, about 500,000 quotes per year for Aetna, Cigna, Coventry, and others

 Maintained and enhanced billing, quoting, and enrollment PHP 5 web applications critical to the consumer, member, small group, and broker blocks of business for Cigna, Ameritas, Coventry, Beazley, AVMA, Metlife, and United Concordia

Freelance Web Developer, Self-employed, Tampa, FL

December 2009 – April 2010

- Saved a bond trading site approximately \$10k per year in wages by automating manual tasks like calculation, tracking, statements, and report generation
- Established a real estate site for a client that interfaced with MLS/IDX listings, alleviating countless hours of coming up with and maintaining own listings

Web Developer at CDPulse, Clearwater, FL (defunct)

August 2006 – December 2009

- Maintained music site which sold CDs & mp3s for hundreds of independent artists online, streamed music through integrated mp3 player, and streamed bands live
- Designed front-end with Photoshop mockups, slicing, and HTML/CSS, and backend with PHP, MySQL, Smarty templating engine and integrated payments through Authorize.net

Technical Skills

- Languages: (proficient): PHP, HTML, CSS, JavaScript. (familiar): C#, Java, Ruby
- Databases: (proficient): MySQL, DB2, SQLite. (familiar): MSSQL, MongoDB
- <u>Frameworks/Libraries</u>: (proficient): Proprietary, Laravel, jQuery, PDFLib. (familiar): Ruby on Rails, Express.js, Angular, React
- Version Control: Git/Github, IBM RTC/CCM, Dimensions
- Services: REST APIs, JSON, SOAP, SAML, AJAX
- <u>Security</u>: OWASP, encryption, payment tokenization, Ping Federate
- Concepts: Object-oriented design, SOLID principles, design patterns
- Tools: PhpStorm, vim, SoapUI, Postman, SASS/LESS, composer, phpunit, vagrant, NPM
- Servers: Apache/Zend Server, Node.js, Linux (CentOS, Arch, Debian/Ubuntu)

Education

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science University of South Florida – *Tampa, FL* December 2009